Felice Picano Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Felice Picano papers
1970-1991
YCAL MSS 761
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.63
(13 boxes)
The papers contain Felice Picano's writings, journals and diaries, and correspondence with his publishers and his friends, including American author Andrew Holleran.
Picano, Felice, 1944-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Felice Picano, 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Felice Picano (1944- )
Felice Picano, American author, editor, playwright, and activist, was born in New York in 1944; he graduated from Queens College in 1964.
Picano was affiliated with a literary group known as the Violet Quill, whose seven members, as men writing for men, are regarded as one of the strongest collective voices of the gay male experience in the post-Stonewall era. Authors Christopher Cox, Robert Ferro, Michael Grumley, Andrew Holleran, Edmund White, George Whitmore, and Picano met several times in 1979, 1980, and 1981 to read aloud from their works in progress. Also on the agenda were discussions of how they could work together to promote recognition, acceptance, and publication of gay literature beyond the boundaries of their own community. Of the VQ writers, Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro were the first to die from AIDS-related complications, both at age 46 in 1988, Grumley on April 28 and Ferro on July 11; they were followed by Whitmore in 1989 and Cox in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The Felice Picano Papers contain writings, journals and diaries, and correspondence with his publishers and his colleague Andrew Holleran.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Writings, 1982-1987. II. Journals and Notebooks, 1970-1989. III. Correspondence and Financial Records, 1973-1989. IV. Other Papers, 1975-1991.
American fiction -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- United States; Gay men's writings, American; Male homosexuality -- Fiction; Violet Quill (Group of writers); Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Holleran, Andrew; Picano, Felice, 1944-
- Writings, 1982-1987; Series I; 5; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by title of work, with miscellaneous writings at the end.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains drafts and finished typescripts of novels, plays, screenplays, and other writings by Picano.
  - "Amber's Wives," typescript, undated; 4 (Box 1)
  - "Ambidextrous," typescript, 1985; 4 (Box 1)
  - "Automatons: a farce", undated
  - "The Bombay Trunk," typescript, 1987; 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Cashmere Coat," typescript, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Deformity Lover and other poems," typescript, undated (Box 1)
  - "Edge Seven," typescript, undated; 4 (Box 1)
  - "Eyes," typescript, undated (Box 1)
  - "Eyes," typescript, undated; 7 (Box 2)
  - "House of Cards," typescript, 1984; 4 (Box 2)
  - "Immortal," typescript, 1986 (Box 2)
  - "Looking-Glass Lives," bound typescript, 1982 (Box 2)
  - "The Lure," typescript, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - "The Lure," typescript, undated; 8 (Box 3)
  - "Lust for Tomorrow," typescript, undated (Box 3)
  - "Men Who Love Me," typescript, undated; 7 (Box 3)
  - "The Mesmerist," typescript, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Mesmerist," typescript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - "Narrative and Curse," typescript, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "One O'clock Jump," typescript, undated (Box 4)
  - "Shadow Master," typescript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - "Slashed to Ribbons," typescript, undated; 11 (Box 4)
  - "Smart as the Devil," typescript, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "To the Seventh Power," typescript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - A-C, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - C-E, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - F, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - F-I, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - L-M, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - M-P, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - P, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
    Contains "Point of View," bound typescript
  - P-R, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - S-T, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - T-V, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - W-Unidentified, miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - Unidentified miscellaneous typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - "Short Pieces," typescript poems, undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - "Interviews," typescripts, undated (Box 5)
  - "Reviews," typescripts, undated; 3 (Box 5)
- Journals and Notebooks, 1970-1989; Series II; 5.42; (6 boxes)
  Series II is arranged roughly chronologically.
  The series contains diaries, notebooks, and journals kept by Picano, some of which have drafts of his writings. The titles cited were assigned by Picano.
  - Diary Vol. 1, 1970 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 2, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 3, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 4, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    Contains a loose sheet of character descriptions.
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 5, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 6, 1974 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 7, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 8, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Diary, Vol 9, 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - Diary, extension of Vol 10, 1976 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 10, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - "The Diary of an Alchemist," Vol 11, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - "The Journal of an Alchemist," Vol 12, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Diary, Vol 13, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Diary, Vol 14, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Diary, Vol 15, 1980-1982 (Box 7)
  - Journals, Vol 16, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Diary, Vol 16, 1982 (Box 7)
  - "The Cashmere Coat / 1. the Pillar of Ice / 2. The Two Tailors / Outline," notebook, 1984 (Box 7)
  - "Outline for Edge Seven / The Cashmere Coat / 2. The Two Tailors," notebook, 1984 (Box 7)
  - "Outline - Edge 7 / Men Who Loved Me pt.1," notebook, 1985 (Box 7)
  - "EDGE 7 Chp3 / Mirror Without a Heart," notebook, 1986 (Box 7)
  - "The Cashmere Coat," notebook, circa 1976 (Box 7)
  - "The Bombay Trunk Act II," notebook, circa 1980 (Box 7)
    Contains journal entries.
  - Journals, Vol 17, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - "Amber's Wives / Book One / Review: A Kingdom in their Heads", notebook, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - "Ambidextrous pt. 1 + prologue / The Cashmere Coat / These Men Speak to Me," notebook, 1983 (Box 7)
  - "Ambidextrous pt.2 A Valentine / Reviews," notebook, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - "Novel: Ambidextrous pt 3 The Effect of Mirrors / Pillar of Ice / Trainor," notebook, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Journal (unlabeled volume), circa 1984 (Box 7)
  - Journals, Vol 18, 1985 (Box 7)
  - "Journals, Vol _", 1985-1986 (Box 8)
  - Journals, Vol 20, 1986-1988 (Box 8)
  - Journals, Vol 21, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
  - Poetry, notebook, 1973 (Box 8)
  - "Reviews / Novel - Confidence - Outline / Poetry," notebook, 1981-1982 (Box 8)
  - "Professor from Peru," notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - "Narrative and Curse / II", notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - Essay, Novel, TV Play and Poems, notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - Essay, Novel and Story, notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - "Men Who Loved Me pt 1," notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Lure," notebook, undated (Box 8)
    Contains newspaper clipping
  - "Poetry / Story: One Way Out," notebook, undated (Box 8)
    Contains bills and prescription.
  - Poetry, notebook, undated (Box 8)
    Also contains lists of music and composers.
  - Poetry, notebook, 1973 (Box 8)
  - "Singles / Blind Man's Bluff," notebook, 1975 (Box 8)
    Lists of books and authors
  - Stories, Novella, Review, Novel and a Story, notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - "Play: Penthouse / Essay: Function of Criticism", notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - Reviews, Short Stories and Essays, notebook, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Essay/Lecture, Poems, Short Fiction and Novel, notebook, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Journal, Revisions, Poems and a Letter, notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - "Re-Fitting," notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - Stories, Novel, Essays and Poems, notebook, 1979 (Box 9)
  - "The Lure," notebooks, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Screenplay for "Eyes," notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - "The Cable Experience / Book One: Testing, Testing," notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - "The Cable Experience / Book Two: Refitting," notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - "The Cable Experience outline" and Poems, notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - "Story: Spinning / Novel: Late in the Season," notebook, 1980 (Box 9)
  - "Confidence, a novel", Story and Reviews, notebook, 1981 (Box 9)
  - "The Mesmerist," notebook, 1975 (Box 9)
  - Novel, Preface and Reviews, notebook, 1982 (Box 9)
  - "Novel: House of Cards pt 2 / Essay: Re-assessing Baudelaire," notebook, 1982 (Box 9)
    Contains a magazine clipping.
  - "EDGE 7," notebooks, circa 1986; 3 (Box 9)
  - Poems, notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - Poetry, notebook, 1974 (Box 9)
  - "The Guest in the Little Red-Brick House," notebook, undated (Box 9)
  - Ficto-Essay, Reviews, Stories, Novel and Poems, notebook, 1980 (Box 10)
  - "Singles," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Stories and Essays, notebook, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Poems, notebook, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Poems, Essays and Short Stories, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "Hypnotism: Some Notes / A Very American Day," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified revisions, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified Story and Journal entries, notebook, circa 1985 (Box 10)
  - Reviews, Story and Poems, notebook, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Reviews and Story, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "Singles," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "Point of View," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "The Cable Experience - outline," loose pages, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified Writings, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Essay, Novels, Reviews and Poetry, notebook, 1981 (Box 10)
  - "The Commandant Comes to Tea," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Poetry, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified Writings, loose pages, undated (Box 10)
  - Poetry, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "Play: Gone with the Titanic," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - "Betrothal at Usk," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Poetry, notebook, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Stories and Reviews, notebook, 1983 (Box 10)
  - "The Mesmerist," notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified writings, notebook, undated (Box 10)
  - Essays, Reviews, Short Stories and Novel, notebook, 1981 (Box 11)
  - "Confidence, a novel," notebook, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
  - Poetry, notebook, 1981 (Box 11)
  - "The Final Flowering of Thomas Wydeslade," notebook, undated (Box 11)
  - Poems, notebook, circa 1973 (Box 11)
  - "Wydeslade / Price of a Watercolor," notebook, undated (Box 11)
  - Poems, loose pages, typed, undated (Box 11)
- Correspondence and Financial Records, 1973-1989; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series III is arranged alphabetically, with financial records at the end.
  The series primarily contains correspondence between Picano and his publishers, his friends Andrew Holleran and Jean Harris, and his agent Jane Rotrosen.
  - General correspondence, A-Z, 1976-1989 (Box 12)
  - Arbor House, 1974-1977 (Box 12)
  - Delacorte Press, 1976-1980 (Box 12)
  - Dell Books, 1976-1979 (Box 12)
  - Harris, Jean, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
  - Holleran, Andrew, 1979-1988 (Box 12)
  - Rotrosen, Jane, 1973-1977 (Box 12)
  - First names (otherwise unidentified), 1975-1981 (Box 12)
  - Financial records, notebook, 1985 (Box 12)
- Other Papers, 1975-1991; Series IV; 1; (1 box)
  Series IV primarily contains issues of magazines kept by Picano. Also present is a small scrapbook with composed pages of clippings, photographs, and printed ephemera.
  - Magazines, titles C-S, 1980-1982 (Box 13)
  - Blueboy magazines, 1980-1981 (Box 13)
  - Christopher Street magazines, 1979-1981; 2 (Box 13)
  - Mandate magazines, 1980-1981 (Box 13)
  - Publishers' catalogs and advertisements, 1975-1980 (Box 13)
  - Articles and reviews, 1975-1991 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous typed and handwritten material, 1980-1991 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 13)
    General note
    Contains a typescript of "Automatons: a farce"